<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dr. CS codes</title><link>http://DrCS.codes/</link><description>Recent content on Dr. CS codes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="http://DrCS.codes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/slides/intro-python/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/slides/intro-python/</guid><description>% Introduction to Computing with Python
Computing Computing is any purposeful activity that marries the representation of some dynamic domain with the representation of some dynamic machine that provides theoretical, empirical or practical understanding of that domain or that machine.
&amp;ndash; Isbell, et. al., (Re)Defining Computing Curricula by (Re)Defining Computing, SIGCSE Bulletin, Volume 41, Number 4, December 2009
Models, Languages, Machines Computing is fundamentally a modelling activity.
A model is a representation of some information, physical reality, or a virtual entity in a manner that can then be interpreted, manipulated, and transformed.</description></item><item><title>Drill - Values and Variables</title><link>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/exercises/values-variables/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/exercises/values-variables/</guid><description>Drill - Values and Variables Introduction Drills are very short exercises designed to exercise the most basic building blocks of modules and programs. In this drill you will create a series of values and assign them to variables to solidify your knowledge of values, variables, operators, and types.
Solution Description For each of the comments below, write the specified Python code. You may do this in the Python interactive shell or by creating a text file that you run from the command line or import into an interactive Python shell (which runs the code).</description></item><item><title>Getting Started</title><link>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/getting-started/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/getting-started/</guid><description>Getting Started Ubuntu/WSL2 If you are using Windows 10 or 11, install WSL2, the Windows Subsystem for Linux, Version 2. WSL2 provides a very nice Linux environment, including a full Linux kernel and distribution of yoru choosing (I will use the latest Ubuntu in demonstrations). You can install the Windows version of Python and all the other tools used in this course, but Python is primarily a Linux/Unix technology and all course demonstrations on Windows will use WSL2.</description></item><item><title>Lessons</title><link>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/lessons/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/lessons/</guid><description>Lessons Session Topic Resources 1 Introduction to Intensive Python Syllabus
Schedule
Meet the Teacher
Video: Getting Started
Exercise: CS 2316 Pre-test
2 Intro to Python Reading: TP 1
Video: Intro to Python
3 Values and Variables Reading: PfP
Video: Values and Variables
Drill - Values and Variables
4 Functions CS1 Python Functions
TP 3</description></item><item><title>Values and Variables</title><link>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/slides/values-variables/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://DrCS.codes/intensive-python/slides/values-variables/</guid><description>Values and Variables ** Languages and Computation
Every powerful language has three mechanisms for combining simple ideas to form more complex ideas:([[http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book-Z-H-10.html][SICP 1.1]])
primitive expressions, which represent the simplest entities the language is concerned with, means of combination, by which compound elements are built from simpler ones, and means of abstraction, by which compound elements can be named and manipulated as units. Today we&amp;rsquo;ll begin learning Python&amp;rsquo;s facilities for primitive expresions, combination, and elementary abstraction.</description></item></channel></rss>