<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Machine-learnings on Dr. CS codes</title><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/</link><description>Recent content in Machine-learnings on Dr. CS codes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/cs4641-intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/cs4641-intro/</guid><description>% Introduction to CS4641
Machine Learning: The Big Idea {height=70%}
Machine Learning: The Big Idea {height=70%}
Machine Learning: The Big Idea {height=70%}
Machine Learning: The Big Idea {height=70%}
Berlin is cold!
Course Logistics Syllabus Schedule Project Getting started</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/error/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/error/</guid><description>% Error and Noise
Error Measures An error measure quantifies the performance of an $h \in \mathcal{H}$, that is, its agreement with the target function $f$.
$$ Error = E(h, f) $$
The target function is unknown and we only have samples from it (our data set, $\mathcal{D}$), so we use a pointwise approximation. Classification error is
$$ e(h(\vec{x}), f(\vec{x})) = \llbracket h(\vec{x}) \ne f(\vec{x}) \rrbracket $$
for some $\vec{x}$, where $\llbracket \cdot \rrbracket$ evaluates to 1 if argument is true, and to 0 if it is false.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/intro-ml/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/intro-ml/</guid><description>% Introduction to Machine Learning
What is learning? &amp;ldquo;Learning is any process by which a system improves performance from experience.&amp;rdquo;
Herbert Simon What is machine learning? The hype answer:
&amp;ldquo;Machine learning is the next Internet&amp;rdquo;
Tony Tether, Director, DARPA &amp;ldquo;Machine learning is the hot new thing&amp;rdquo;
John Hennessy, President, Stanford &amp;ldquo;Machine learning is today’s discontinuity&amp;rdquo;
Jerry Yang, CEO, Yahoo &amp;ldquo;Machine learning is the new electricity&amp;rdquo; -Andrew Ng, Chief Scientist Baidu</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/linear-classification/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/linear-classification/</guid><description>% Linear Classification
The Linear Model In the next few lectures we will
extend the perceptron learning algorithm to handle non-linearly separable data, explore online versis batch learning, learn three different learning settings &amp;ndash; classification, regression, and probability estimation learn a fundamental concept in machine learning: gradient descent see how the learning rate hyperparameter The Linear Model Recall that the linear model for binary classification is:
$$ \mathcal{H} = {h(\vec{x}) = sign(\vec{w}^T \cdot \vec{x})} $$</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/linear-regression/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/linear-regression/</guid><description>% Linear Regression
The Linear Model So far we&amp;rsquo;ve dealt with classification, where the target function maps feature vectors to discrete classes, but the linear model is more versatile. Consider the credit analysis problem:
{height=30%}
We can use the linear model to learn
a yes/no (perceptron) an arbitrary real number (linear regression) a probability (logistic regression) As we&amp;rsquo;ll see later, we can even learn to separate classes that are not linearly separable due to their nature, not noise in the data set.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/ml-practice/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/ml-practice/</guid><description>% Practical Considerations in Machine Learning
Overfitting Overfitting has occurred when your training error decreases and your test error increases.
The primary cause of overfitting is noise in the data set.
More complex models are more likely to overfit.
Regularization Constraining the model to prevent overfitting.
Validation The most important use of validation is for model selection.
Cross-Validation? A resampling technique
Occam&amp;rsquo;s Razor Sampling Bias Data Snooping</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/ml-theory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/ml-theory/</guid><description>% Computational Learning Theory
Decidability Computation
Decidability &amp;ndash; which problems have algorithmic solutions Machine Learning
Feasibility &amp;ndash; what assumptions must we make to trust that we can learn an unknown target function from a sample data set Complexity Complexity is a measure of efficiency. More efficient solutions use fewer resources.
Computation &amp;ndash; resources are time and space
Time complexity &amp;ndash; as a function of problem size, $n$, how many steps must an algorithm take to solve a problem Space complexity &amp;ndash; how much memory does an algorithm need Machine learning &amp;ndash; resource is data</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/numpy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/numpy/</guid><description>% NumPy
Numerical Python Provides efficient storage and operations on dense data buffers, i.e., arrays.
ndarray is the fundamental object Vectorized operations on arrays Broadcasting File IO amd memory-mapped files In [1]: import numpy as np NumPy Array Element Types Arrays have elements of homogeneous data type
In [2]: a = np.array([1, 2, 3.14]) In [3]: type(a) Out[3]: numpy.ndarray In [4]: a Out[4]: array([ 1. , 2. , 3.14]) In [5]: type(a[0]) Out[5]: numpy.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/pandas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/pandas/</guid><description>% Pandas % Data Manipulation in Python
Pandas Built on NumPy Adds data structures and data manipulation tools Enables easier data cleaning and analysis import pandas as pd pd.set_option(&amp;#34;display.width&amp;#34;, 120) That last line allows you to display DataFrames with many columns without wrapping.
Pandas Fundamentals Three fundamental Pandas data structures:
Series - a one-dimensional array of values indexed by a pd.Index Index - an array-like object used to access elements of a Series or DataFrame DataFrame - a two-dimensional array with flexible row indices and column names Series from List In [4]: data = pd.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/pla/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/pla/</guid><description>% Linear Separators % The Perceptron Learning Algorithm
Learning Problem Setup Every machine learning problem contains the following elements:
An input $\vec{x}$ (though, as we&amp;rsquo;ll see later, $\vec{x}$ can be a list aof arbitrary feature values, not necessarily a vector) An unkown target function $f: \mathcal{X} \rightarrow \mathcal{Y}$ A data set $\mathcal{D}$ A learning model, which consists of a hypothesis class $\mathcal{H}$, and a learning algorithm. A learning algorithm uses elements of $\mathcal{D}$ to estimate parameters of of a particular $h(\vec{x})$ from $\mathcal{H}$ which maps every $\vec{x}$ to an element of $\mathcal{Y}$.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/spark-intro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/machine-learning/slides/spark-intro/</guid><description>% Introduction to Spark
Apache Spark &amp;ldquo;Unified computing engine&amp;rdquo;
cluster manager for running programs distributed across multiple computers (&amp;ldquo;nodes&amp;rdquo;) Spark cluster manager, YARN, or Mesos libraries for parallel data processing Spark Applications Driver process runs main() function on a node in the cluster Maintains information about the Spark application Responds to user&amp;rsquo;s program or input Analyzes, distributes, and schedules work across executors Executor processes Carry out work assigned by driver Report state of computation to driver {height=30%}</description></item></channel></rss>