<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shareds on Dr. CS codes</title><link>https://DrCS.codes/shared/</link><description>Recent content in Shareds on Dr. CS codes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://DrCS.codes/shared/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://DrCS.codes/shared/text-editors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/shared/text-editors/</guid><description>Introduction to Text Editors for Young Programmers Text is the raw material of the craft of programming. You should become good at manipulating text. The first thing you should do is pick a good cross-platform text editor and learn it well. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t already done so, this guide will help you choose one. The next thing you should do is learn regular expressions, and the next thing after that is learn UNIX and one of its command shells, probably bash.</description></item><item><title>Git</title><link>https://DrCS.codes/shared/git/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/shared/git/</guid><description>Git This guide provides a brief introduction to Git and GitHub
Installation Linux You almost certainly have it already. If not,
Debian-based (like Ubuntu):
sudo apt install git Red Hat-based (like Fedora):
sudo yum install git Note: I haven&amp;rsquo;t used Fedora in many years, so double check that.
macOS If you have a Mac, I recommend Homebrew. Then installing git is easy:
brew install git It&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to update brew and your brew packages first:</description></item><item><title>IntelliJ</title><link>https://DrCS.codes/shared/intellij/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://DrCS.codes/shared/intellij/</guid><description>IntelliJ/Pycharm Almost all professional Java and Scala development teams use IntelliJ IDEA, an IDE (integrated development environment) for Java and many other languages, including Python and Go. Most professional Python programmers use PyCharm, or IntelliJ with the Python plugin, which is equivalent to PyCharm. JetBrains has a well-earned reputation for making the best developer tools. It is possible to get much of the same functionality with VS Code by installing several plugins, but the quality of the plugins is usually inferior.</description></item></channel></rss>